They call this place
the Land of Great Thirst.
The great Karoo desert,
South Africa.
We are in one of the most
inhospitable places on Earth.
Ten participants.
Whoever can stay
the longest wins.
It's pretty simple.
I found the baboons.
There's ten of them, but
I only have five arrows.
This place is dry, dry, dry.
The sun's beating
down on you every day.
I'm so tired,
and I'm so thirsty.
Oh, man.
I really don't feel
safe drinking this water.
This is a place to be,
if not feared,
treated with a lot of respect.
I changed my mind!
Oh, look at the size
of that thing.
There's a big herd
of wildebeest right there.
- Rhino tracks.
- Meat.
Back on the menu, boys.
They call Cape buffalo
the black death for a reason.
They'll just
straight up kill you.
We don't control the game.
Here you go.
Flooding.
This is nothing
compared to what's coming.
It hurts so much, man.
It's freaking ice.
So the question is,
how strong of a mind
do you need to have
to win this?
Whoo!
What the
did I get myself into?
Long cold night.
The last one to tap walks
out of here with 500 grand.
This is one of
the hardest things
that a person can do
in their life.
Oh, my gosh.
It's another
great day in Africa.
Day one is just beginning.
Can't wait to start
this journey.
This season is the first time
we're going to be
in South Africa.
Whoo!
There they go!
We're in uncharted territory
for "Alone."
Wow. Spectacular.
This is dramatically different
than any of the other seasons.
It's actually
a whole new game.
This is an arid
desert environment.
There it goes.
And going from extreme heat
with no moisture in the air
to getting plunged
into the darkness
and the cold at night,
mixed in with all
of the dangerous animals
is going to be brutal.
Holy [bleep].
Sorry, Mom.
If ever there was
a thought in your mind
about whether
this was real or fake,
it feels pretty real now.
Being immersed
in the wild life
is going to be
freakin' insane.
Cape buffalo,
when they come at you,
they want you dead.
There goes my last link
to civilization.
There are venomous snakes.
There are venomous scorpions,
extremely poisonous
plants here.
There are ungulates
with huge horns
defending themselves
that could skewer you
like shish kebab.
There is any number of things
that could take you
out of the game
or out of life in a heartbeat.
We're not
in the Arctic anymore.
We're in a desert,
so water's a big thing.
Dehydration is a killer,
but we got to work
for our water.
You have to collect it
and boil it,
because water illness
is a big concern.
They're leaving me alone!
Yee-ha!
You get ten survival experts
with ten items,
and you go drop them off
in the middle of nowhere
with nobody.
You're going to have animals
trying to eat you
and Mother Nature
trying to kill you.
And between all that,
the last one standing
wins half a million dollars.
What did I just
sign up for, guys?
This competition is crazy.
If you're not set up
to survive
in this kind of environment,
I mean, it can get you quick.
Get out of here.
Whoo!
That's what I'm talking about.
No drop shock, baby.
Let's do this.
Let me show you all what
I'm working with here.
Look at this.
I like this spot.
I like it.
I'm right on the lake, boys.
It's a big lake.
I'll show you
this excited face of mine.
Oh, man, guys.
Holy crap.
I wouldn't call it drop shock,
but, damn,
it sure is different.
First thing, let's calm down.
Just chill right
the [bleep] out, Will.
I know this is cool...
but you got to make
a plan of attack.
You got to see
what the hell you're going
to be doing out here first.
I got to get some
of this water.
But I tell you right now,
from looking at it, it's muddy.
It reminds me of back home,
Lake Casa Blanca--
brown-green water.
Hey, hey, hey.
Keep on going.
Keep going.
Last two!
I'm an exotic trapper.
I catch, transport,
and house exotic animals.
I work with species
from Africa, Asia, Australia.
If you can imagine,
like, a cattle rancher,
it's basically what we do
but with exotics.
They sell hunts
and stuff like that
on the species
that aren't endangered.
Even though it's powered
by the hunting industry,
it's really having
a big effect on conservation.
A lot of the animals
that we raise
have gone extinct
in their country of origin.
So now countries
are looking to Texas
to repopulate their supplies.
I would classify myself
as a primitive enthusiast.
I definitely don't do this
for a living,
but I have what it takes to
take one of these big animals.
I have enough knowledge
of hunting.
I know how to stalk.
I know how to ambush.
I know how to make a blind.
I feel like my skills
are suited for this location
more than any other.
I'm a very, very
physically capable guy.
I'm a very mentally strong
guy, you know?
I was made for this, bro.
Now we wait.
Are you going to miss Dada?
My wife and my boy,
they're my sole reason
for being on this Earth now,
you know?
He's loving that, dude.
My main goal is providing
for my family
and creating a legacy
that my boy can be proud of.
He's just a baby right now,
but when he starts
being a little kid
and, you know,
starts becoming a man
and understanding the world
with the foundation
that I hope to give him,
you know, I hope he sees
this sense of legacy.
- Get it. Get it. Get it.
- Get it, Dada.
If I was ever going
to get a chance
to prove to the world
who William Lamb is,
what I can do,
this is it, man.
This is now or never.
This water is gross.
You will get sick if you drink
this without disinfecting it.
So I'm gonna start
processing some water.
So get my pot.
Just going to cover it...
with the bandanna...
And dip it in.
And that should strain out
all that big stuff.
Whenever you get water
to process, to boil,
you want to cut down on
anything going into the water.
You want to kind of do
your best at filtering it.
Oh, yeah.
Look at that.
I got to get a fire going,
get this water on there.
In this area,
the water is horrible.
You got to understand
that all these animals
are coming to drink here,
physically getting
in the water.
All of them are crapping
And not only that,
I'm on a continent
to where my body is not used
to any of the amoebas,
any of the bacteria.
So I definitely
don't want to drink
any of this water unprocessed.
Get a little tripod action.
Nothing fancy.
Man, this water is rank.
You can smell it.
Not only are we in an area
where its elevated heat,
super, super windy,
so it's just drying you out
like a piece of jerky
the entire time you're there.
Along with all the physical
exertion, you're sweating.
You're using all these fluids.
You have to replace
them pretty regularly.
I'm going to have to have
water going 24-7, you know,
always having
a pot of water cool
or in the process
of purifying water.
Staying hydrated is going
to be a full-time job.
All right.
Let's let this boil.
I'm going to go set up a fish--
a hook and line.
After this boils,
I'll let it cool.
But maybe I can go get
a fish in the meantime.
They're gone.
That's it. It's just me.
Look, just me.
Okay.
I have water here.
That's good.
I'm just going to--
I'm going to camp here tonight,
for sure, on this little beach.
I like being this close
to water.
I'm going to explore up here
a little bit.
That's my plan.
Get water going.
And then tonight
with my headlamp,
I can do little things.
Okay, calm down.
We'll go
for a little walkabout.
Here in South Africa,
the land is characterized
by open grasslands and plains
and rocky hills
with cliffs and boulders.
So many rocks.
You got to be careful.
My strategy is to find
where everything is.
I'm not sure what the
resources
are going to be here.
I need to explore
all my territory.
I can't believe I'm on "Alone."
If I don't catch fish
or shoot something,
I don't eat.
Like, that's very real.
My hope is to find where
the animals are living,
where they're coming in
to find water,
because hunting
is my priority.
But right now, day one,
just need to look around
and take it all in.
Look at these.
I don't know. I think
those are baboon tracks.
We're going to have problems
because they're
like little people
that are going to, like,
attack you,
rip you up, steal your stuff.
Hmm.
That's interesting.
Karen--Karen, touch it.
It's pretty dry.
By the way, I named
my camera Karen.
So we'll see how we
get along out here.
Okay.
Never truly been alone.
I've either had
family, friends.
I mean,
there's always somebody.
Nice rainy day.
I've been with my boyfriend,
Brady, for seven years.
We live completely off-grid
in Montana.
We have the big totes that
we catch the rainwater with,
so this is how
we do our dishes.
You have to be tough.
You don't get all the comforts
of a regular household.
Having an outhouse
for a bathroom,
and having to cross a river
to get to the house,
it makes you strong
physically.
Today we're going to make
a natural water-filter system.
Charcoal.
And I'm just going to
throw it in on top.
From the river.
The practical skills
I'm most confident in
would be hunting...
All right.
We can eat beaver tonight.
Fishing...
Oh, yeah.
Fire building, because I've
been doing it my whole life.
Aha.
The $500,000
is important to me
because I run
Long Acres Rescue,
and we help wild burros
and mustangs find new homes.
That's Whiskey.
That money would help me
rescue more animals.
But I want to do "Alone" to
show that women are stronger
than they think they are.
I'm going to be that girl
that they were like,
I should have paid
more attention
to what she was doing,
because I'm a force
to be reckoned with.
So many noises.
Was that a baboon?
Um...
I'm just trying to
see if I can see it,
figure out what it is.
Freaking baboons
over on that ridge.
They're yelling at me.
So we're going to stay clear.
Don't go there.
Oh, my gosh, those baboons
don't like me being here.
They gave us horror stories
of the baboons.
They play dead.
You shoot them, you go up to
them, and they're not dead,
and the rest of them
turning on you.
They're just yelling.
I don't want them
anywhere near me.
There's more poop.
Those baboons are yelling.
We can share, guys.
We can share.
You get that side,
I get this side, capisce?
These freaking baboons
are following me.
I don't like it.
I think there's ten of them.
I only have five arrows
right now.
Baboons can be
in troops of 60 to 100.
They have giant fangs.
They can steal your stuff,
get into camp.
And I want them to know that
this is my area now,
not theirs.
I'm going to let them know
that I'm here now.
This is my spot!
Get! Get!
Okay.
They seem to be going up, so
hopefully they stay going up.
But they're not happy.
Okay, we got to head back,
get camp set up for the night.
I'm not worried about any
other animals, just baboons.
I actually love trying
to get close to animals,
seeing how close I can get.
I've been charged
three times by grizzlies.
I am not afraid
of a Cape buffalo
or a rhino coming in.
I'm pretty much back to
where they dropped me off.
The good news, guys--
got to look
on the bright side--
I still see my stuff.
So baboons have not came
and taken it.
So that's good news.
I think I'm going to set
everything up over here.
And if I have a pokey tree...
baboons shouldn't come
from above, right?
So I think I'm just going to
kind of put all my stuff here.
Okay.
All right, I'm going to show
the whole lake right now.
It's amazing, it's beautiful,
and it's so quiet.
After the helicopter leaves,
forget about it.
Oh, my God.
I think I'm gonna
like this area.
Check it out, guys.
Awesome.
Oh, my God.
All alone.
I put the GoPro
on the walking stick.
That way's easier for me
to explore a little bit.
Ooh, a lot of loose rocks here.
I got to be
really careful here.
Very easy to--
Look at that.
Very old, but that means
they come around here.
It's getting very hot...
so I can't be spending
too much time walking around.
And I'm from Cuba...
Where it's humid, hot.
Now for some 3D archery.
My name is Pablo Arguelles.
I'm originally from Cuba,
and now I live
in Jacksonville, Florida.
Alligators, that's one
thing here in Florida
we got a lot of.
I lived in Cuba
until I was 11 years old.
My dad wasn't a part
of the Communist Party.
They didn't believe
in the Communist dictatorship
and the way of thinking.
We lived
in a tough environment
and poor conditions.
I know how to build
different kinds of shelters.
I know how to fish.
Ugh! Actually,
it feels good on my back.
I can hunt.
I can trap.
I love things outside,
because it felt free.
Like, forget
about the government.
Say whatever you want here.
There's nobody around.
Boom, baby!
So we left in 1980--
me, my parents, and my sister.
My brothers
had to stay behind.
And to this day,
I view survival as doing
whatever it takes to make it.
That was not easy,
doing it by yourself,
but that's the way
you got to do it.
You got to use your teeth,
whatever tools you got.
I'm doing "Alone,"
because to me,
it's going to be
the most incredible experience
of my life.
I quit my job to go on this
thing full-force, nonstop.
I didn't want nothing
to be on my way.
I feel very confident
that I can do anything.
I'm going to be
the first Cuban on "Alone."
And this, to me,
is honoring my parents
because they fought so hard
for us to have a better life.
Qué bueno.
Yeah.
And for them
to see me winning this...
Whoo!
It would be incredible.
$500,000, for sure,
will be a life-changing event
for me and my fiancée,
and I can help my parents
as much as possible,
whatever they need.
To me, this is
the American Dream.
Check this water out.
It looks pretty nasty.
I got to boil it really good
and eventually make
a water filter.
Here, drinking water
is going to be a major thing
because I can overheat
and get hyperthermia.
But what if I get something
from this water
and then I go home sick,
or who knows
what's going to happen?
So I'm going to do
a coyote well.
All right, I'm going to try
to make a coyote well
and see if this works.
Hopefully it does...
and we can get
a little bit cleaner water.
A coyote well--basically,
you dig a hole away
from the edge of the water,
and then the earth itself
is going to start filtering
the water.
Oh, yeah.
It's getting nice
and soft in there.
It's going to fill
that well up.
It's going to be
dirty at first,
so you got to empty it
until the water starts
getting cleaner and cleaner.
There you go.
It's getting muddy now.
There we go.
I see water.
Awesome.
Then you can boil the water,
and it'll be a lot safer
to drink.
Every problem, to me,
has a solution.
You just got to take your time
and find the solution
to the problem.
And I think I developed that
from my dad.
Use what you got,
because in Cuba,
you don't have nothing.
You got to make things work
for real.
And that's
the kind of person I am.
All right.
Now we just have to wait
till it fills up...
And hopefully works.
I think...
I think I've got
a beautiful spot.
This is [bleep] stunning.
So I've got access to this
valley and this little gully,
it looks like.
And this proximity to water
is pretty spectacular.
We're going to
need a lot of water
to keep ourselves
going out here.
And that's why I chose
to bring a water bottle,
so that I could keep
clean water with me,
sipping throughout the day.
Oh, got some prickly pear.
Well, that'll be a good snack
at some point.
Whoa.
Oh, my God.
I thought that was a rock.
That's not a rock.
That's a baboon.
Holy [bleep], that's huge.
Why don't you guys
stay up there,
and I'll stay down
here for a while?
They seem pretty content
up there...
for now.
Let's head back and go fishing.
I know they can see me.
There's no way they can't.
I probably spent a couple
of hundred nights out
in some different locations
and different environments,
but here it just feels
that little bit harder.
Fire time!
Satisfying noise.
Ah, crackle!
The real connection
to the outdoors
started when I was a teenager.
Yeah, boy!
The army cadets
at school gave me
this opportunity
to go out in the elements,
and that was fantastic.
Preparation, patience
and practice.
I grew up in South London.
Just before university,
I ended up going
over to Asia and India
and traveling quite a lot.
And that sort of opened
my eyes up to the world.
And that's how I sort of
ended up in New Zealand.
This is Anakiwa
in the Marlborough Sounds.
I have been
an outdoor educator
for about nine years, worked
as an operations manager
for an outdoor-education
charity for the last two.
Whilst it's also
about learning the hard skills
of living outside...
You can already see when pull
it apart how fibrous it is.
See that?
Some of the most rewarding
parts of the work
has been when that light bulb
goes off in a student's mind
and they do something
that they didn't think
they were capable of.
There you have it.
This trap will catch things.
I could use this as bait
for other fish.
The reason I think I can take
this challenge on
is because, ultimately,
when you get out there,
it's the challenge
against yourself.
I do like pushing myself.
And so, for me,
this is that opportunity
to do that before I devote
myself again to service.
I'm going to miss creature
comforts, for sure,
but I'm also going to miss
my partner, Maddie.
She has been so supportive.
She said she doesn't mind
how long I'm out here,
but she does want me
to come home in one piece.
$500,000 is a lot of money.
You know,
we could potentially buy
a little plot of land
somewhere.
But for me, "Alone"
is that real opportunity
to learn the things that
I haven't learnt about me.
Beautiful place.
There's already stuff
splashing around down here.
I'm going to be hoping
to focus on getting fish
and whatever plants I can find
in the area, to start with.
If I can sustain myself
on that,
then I'll be able
to go hunting.
Got a little praying mantis.
That is going to be bait.
My fishing is generally
with a beer in one hand
and as many hooks as you want.
Oh, it's dirty.
I'm wondering if that
water's any good.
It will boil off.
Let me get you, little fishy.
The water is filled with stuff
that's of danger to us.
Obviously, I'm going
to be boiling my water.
But with that, being conscious
of things like fish,
if I catch one
and then touch my bottle
with dirty water,
I then need to boil my bottle.
I'm going to be thinking
about clean water constantly.
.
This isn't going well.
You just don't even
know how deep it is.
Probably wasted
an hour around here.
Let's go.
I feel like my body is saying,
hey, it's time to take a poo,
but I haven't eaten anything.
So the plan is getting
some water on.
And while the water
is boiling,
get my first go
with the prickly pears.
I feel I've been fortunate
enough to work
in a lot of different places
around the world,
a lot of different climates,
a lot of different
environments,
and I've learnt how to adapt
to different places.
It's hard to tell if I've
gotten all the hairs off.
There's still other little
soft ones floating around.
And those look like the ones
that might not cause
a problem on the way in
but potentially on the way out.
"Alone" is one hell
of a competition.
It's not just about surviving
with limited items.
It's also about learning
that environment.
Okay, that's it. I've got to be
a lot more vigorous.
Quite a big part
of Outward Bound
is not knowing your schedule
and not knowing
what's coming next
and just learning to roll
with the punches.
They don't actually
taste too bad.
So it's gonna be
a great opportunity
to practice all those
mindfulness skills
that I've been
educating others on.
It's amazing how
just a little something
can just give me
a little bit of a boost.
All right.
Let's work out
what I need to lie down in.
Well, this gonna be
my temporary shelter
for the night.
It's like a little lean-to.
Part of the tarp,
I used as a floor.
That way I'm not
completely on the ground,
knowing there's scorpions here.
I will completely agree
it is not great.
Small shelter,
but it will hopefully
keep me warm.
Just need to know
that I can get food
before I start wasting energy
making this place all luxurious
and digging it down
and all that sort of stuff.
Before I waste
too much energy doing that,
I need to know
that I can get energy.
So I'm gonna sit here
and drink my water.
I can't help wondering what's
going on with everybody else
and how they're doing.
Mm.
I keep getting
flashes of, like,
Will and Colton
and Kelsey and Jit.
Oh, my God, Dug and Doug.
Oh, God.
Pablo--ooh, yes.
I just saw a fish jump.
Before it gets dark,
I'm going to throw a line in
and see what's possible
and then start to think about,
where am I
going to sleep tonight?
Yeah.
Well, it'd be nice
to catch a fish.
The moon's coming up.
Karen, look at the moon.
Okay, I got to flip you around
so you can see this moon.
It's wild, what I'm doing,
just living under the stars
in South Africa.
I'm definitely gonna sleep
under the stars
for the first few nights.
And there's the moon.
I grew up
in Northern Wisconsin,
so I'm not worried
about being cold.
I just want to be simple
and focus on hunting.
Super cool.
Just got to make it
till daylight.
You hear that?
Damn, man.
But I guess I'm gonna
have to get used to that.
Smoked prickly pear.
I'm excited.
You hear that?
Freaking baboons.
The baboons are pretty loud.
I heard one on my side
of the river, screaming.
Hopefully, they just
stay away tonight.
I just woke up,
stoked the fire a little bit.
I ended up moving the fire
closer to me this way.
Help keep me warm tonight.
Whew! Okay.
So this is Katie, "Alone,"
season 12, night one.
And look what I just
managed to bring in--
an Orange River mudfish.
I'm just going to take it
over to the fire
and cook it for dinner.
Anyway, first night in,
I've got a fish.
Here we go.
Mmm.
It's just like back home.
It's crazy.
What is it with
plants and prickles?
Just harvesting breakfast--
fish soup with acacia seeds
and buffalo leaves.
I feel really confident
that I'm gonna be able
to keep bringing fish in.
But I've been thinking
a lot about plant food
as a supplement
to make sure that
I've got a lot of those
alternatives dialed in,
so that even if I don't have
protein on one day,
I've still got other food
to eat that's psychologically
keeping me in the game.
Indigenous people
back home in Australia
used to eat these seeds,
the acacia seeds.
It's something that made them
extremely strong.
Hey, this is
the beautiful coastline
where I live.
I'm Katie Ridge, and I live
on the East Coast
of Australia.
I'm a mom, and I live
with my two kids.
And my world really revolves
around what I do.
I run a school
called Nature Philosophy,
which teaches survival skills,
nature connection,
and sacred ceremony.
And it's been something
I've been doing for 20 years.
See that?
That's food.
I'd like to think of myself
as a jack of many trades
and master of some.
I'm not just a bow hunter
or I'm not just a fisher.
I can do lots
of different skills.
So these are all
some of my baskets.
Traps, shelter,
construction, fire.
I feel really confident
fishing.
I've done a lot of harvesting
of bush foods
for big groups of people,
long 10-day processes
of how to ferment toxic foods
into edible breads.
And I know that that'll
actually give me an edge.
It's beautiful.
I feel like I'm unique
for season 12
because I'm an Aussie,
so I've had a lot
of experience
in arid environments.
You.
I'm here to win
and support my kids.
I could buy us
a house to live in.
I've been having to rent,
so this would be
a huge thing
for me and my kids.
I'm following what feels right
in my heart,
and I'm not
fully understanding
where it's taking me.
But I know that this is
exactly where I'm meant to be.
Bye!
See you guys.
all: Bye!
I can smell an animal.
Ooh, yeah, that's strong.
They ran up the hill.
But if I push on it now,
it'll avoid this whole area.
This is a whole massive channel
that runs all the way
down here to the water.
This is the superhighway.
Check it out.
This is the sort of
country that just hides
everything from you at first.
And then you start to realize
there's food
all over the place.
All right, guys.
See those little things
sticking up on the rocks?
Those are baboons.
Some "Jungle Book" for you.
I'm probably in their spot.
This is probably where
they come down
to the water to drink.
All right.
I'm gonna take my bow,
go up there,
and just see
if it pushes them off,
see if they get aggressive.
Once I go up there,
I imagine I'll push them off.
But if they come back down
and try to come mess
with my [bleep],
I'm going to have to come
back down.
All right.
Let's see what happens,
and then I'll scout
some hunting spots.
My job in the exotic
animal industry,
it's incredibly fun,
rewarding.
You get to work with species
no one ever gets to see.
You're hands-on,
literally, with them.
It's good to know that
even with me making noise...
But baboons are
one of the animals
that I have never had
any interaction with.
Not only are they
pretty vicious,
but they can be
a pain in the ass.
They can come into your camp,
just ransack your stuff.
And when you're trying
to survive on ten items,
any one of those items
gets messed up,
that can mean the game
for you right there.
All right.
I made it
to the top of the hill.
I hear those damn
baboons again.
I don't want to go too far
from my camp.
There's a ton of animals
out here.
Over on my left,
I see two big black outlines.
I hope they're not
Cape buffalo.
But on the right,
I see a big herd of kudu.
They got big horns.
Whoa.
.
Oh, well.
It'd be a bad idea
to take an animal that big
right now, though.
It's just too much animal.
Not ready.
All right.
Let's see what else
we can find.
Oh, look at this.
My coyote well is right there.
Water is so dirty.
Wow.
Let me take you deep inside.
I don't know how contaminated
this water is.
I know I got to stay
hydrated, for sure,
but I don't want to get sick
from it or something worse.
So I need to make sure
from now on I filter somehow.
Because, otherwise,
you're going to have
problems later on.
Got to try something else.
All right.
I'm gonna use my bandana
to put on top of this
so it helps filter it
a little bit more.
I think a single layer
should be fine,
and then boil it really good.
Something so simple here
as just getting water
becomes a big challenge.
It's going to be
a lot of work.
But I think I ended up
the way I am now,
going through
experience good and bad,
and the many challenges
that have come in my life.
It's time to start
making a fire.
But then you overcome that
and go, this got me here.
There she goes.
I believe when
you try really hard
and you really want something,
you got to go 100%.
All right.
Whatever happens after that
is out of my hands,
but at least I went for it.
That's why I quit my job
to focus on this thing 100%,
because I didn't want
any distraction.
So I know I can be here
for the long run.
Yeah, it should be good.
Oh, God, it feels good,
even though it's hot.
Yes.
It's crazy.
Something so simple
becomes a challenge.
I survived the first night.
No baboons came and attacked
me, so that's good.
I do push-ups every morning,
so I'm going to do
my morning push-ups.
Okay, let's go
on a little walk.
You can only shoot animals
with whatever poundage bow
you have,
and you're at a disadvantage
if you shoot a lower poundage.
And so I brought
a 50-pound bow.
I can pull it back,
but it's just a matter
of how often and how much.
But I'm very confident
I can shoot out
to 30 yards and kill something
with my 50-pound bow.
I hear monkeys.
Stupid baboons.
I think this season is
gonna be maybe
a little easier
due to the weather.
We're not dealing
with negative 30s.
with the snow.
We're gonna see more big game.
But I think people are
underestimating
how hard it's gonna be
to get game.
Let's follow this trail.
I think people are
just gonna think
there's game everywhere.
I can just go out
and shoot something.
Look, we're almost at the top.
That's where I want to be.
Okay.
Oh, guys, look.
Look, look, look, look, look.
Do you see it?
It's a waterbuck.
Sucks.
I can't shoot those.
Those are 60-pound animals,
meaning you need
a 60-pound bow.
So I can't shoot them,
'cause I only have
a 50-pound bow.
All right.
Can't do anything about it.
Move on.
I just heard something bark
ov--
I don't know what that is.
I don't see any animals.
I got to get down low.
I got to get
down low.
Oh, my God.
I'm shaking. I'm shaking.
Oh, my God, I got a warthog.
He's not down yet.
I got to go finish him.
You got him.
My legs are shaking.
Okay, that one was a good shot,
went all the way through.
I saw it come out
the other side.
I'm sorry.
Oh, my goodness.
Okay, its dead.
It's officially dead.
This is my first
recurve kill ever.
I shoot a compound bow
back home when I go hunting.
So coming on the show,
I needed to learn recurve.
This is warthog.
With my bow.
Oh, God.
I'm very proud.
I'm glad I had patience.
Coming into "Alone,"
over eight weeks
I shot three times a day,
every single day,
rain or shine.
I would shoot
until I was tired.
I'm very proud that
I can pull a 50-pound bow.
Okay, you guys,
now the work begins.
I got to get going,
'cause it's gonna get hot.
I'm not too far from camp,
maybe half a mile.
I'm gonna see what I can do
to drag her back whole.
Um...[sighs] Man.
Okay.
I am concerned
about the sun
wrecking the meat.
I am concerned about
the flies laying eggs
on the meat.
Oh, my gosh, she's so heavy.
The meat's going to spoil
very fast.
I need to get the meat
to camp as soon as possible.
Nope. Okay.
Well...
She's not even halfway in.
Seriously?
There's no way
I can get up with her.
The warthog has to weigh
at least 100 pounds.
I know a lot of it is bone.
I know a lot of it is guts.
Here's the heart.
It is impossible to drag
this heavy of an animal
with the rocks here.
I need to quarter the warthog.
That is what just
has to happen for me
to get the warthog
back to camp.
I don't want to waste
any meat.
That's just disrespectful
to the animal.
I'm not worried about
how many calories
I put into preserving it.
It's just respect to me.
I got the whole pig back.
Now I have to get
a smoker built.
I'm building
an open tripod smoker
because it is
a quicker process
and I need a smoker
right away.
I found a part of
a blue bush tree.
I'm going to use
blue bush sticks,
tie them together,
and then build a rack
so I can lay my meat out.
I also need to build
a grill so that I can
cook some of the meat
so I can eat it tonight.
Flies are getting bad.
I've got to get this
on the fire.
The flies came in really fast.
They can lay eggs instantly
and the meat is
gonna be ruined.
Heck, yeah, guys, look at this.
Warthog backstrap.
That's dinner tonight.
Gosh golly, so many ants.
The ants also found
the warthog meat,
and I keep having
to brush them off.
I just got to get this meat
off this bone.
It's a lot of work.
So I'm going to put the meat
in between the two
layers of my tarp
laid out flat,
so I'm sleeping next
to my meat to make sure
nothing gets it
and it stays cool.
Out here, a predator
is not going to come in
when I'm right there.
They're going to smell
the human.
They're going to run away.
I'm tired,
but we got meat smoking,
and that's dinner.
Yum!
So I got to go get firewood.
I got to boil more water,
cook some more meat,
keep the smoker going.
Getting there.
We're getting there.
I'm only taking all day,
but we're getting there.
Okay.
Almost done.
Okay, here we go.
First bite, warthog.
Overcooked that one.
That was crunchy.
That's okay.
It smells like warthog.
It's okay.
It's all good.
It's food.
Ooh, I have salt.
I can put salt on this, guys.
I forgot I have salt.
I brought salt.
What am I doing?
Okay, I'm going to grab it.
I am so excited
and so happy
that I made
the last minute decision
to bring salt
as one of my 10 items.
Okay.
Hallelujah.
Sprinkle a little salt.
I brought salt because
the heat and the sun
is going to take all
the electrolytes out of you
here in South Africa.
Oh, that's good.
Mm, mm, mm.
Even though this meat
is delicious,
it's the cherry on top
to have a little seasoning,
a little salt in there.
It is phenomenal.
It is a morale booster
like you can't even imagine.
It's like the fat off
a prime rib or something.
It's so exciting
that I have food.
This warthog gives me
the energy and the will
to continue to hunt
and harvest animals
and stay out here
for a long time.
I'm just lounging in
South Africa eating a warthog.
No big deal. No big deal.
Doesn't even feel like
I'm away from home.
Like, I know I am,
but I don't know.
It's weird.
The belly's already gurgling.
That can shut up.
I'm gonna get that fish.
You watch.
I'm gonna get a fish,
and then I'm gonna
get more fish.
And then I'm gonna be like, bah.
And I'll get myself a meal.
And then I'm gonna also
deck this place out
and it's gonna be pimpin'.
Yeah, let me get up.
I'm gonna need to find bait.
Something stinky, smelly,
something rotten, old,
hopefully to entice
the fish up.
Once I've gotten one fish,
I'll be able to bait
others in.
But it's about getting
that first bit of bait.
I'm just gonna walk
the shorefront now,
see if I can find
anything useful,
like maybe some crabs.
I mean, I am sure
that I could probably
survive on prickly pear,
but that isn't really
why I came here.
So when we look
at survival situations
that people have been put in,
more often than not,
it's not their
technical skills,
it's their will to survive
and their mindset
that has kept them going.
Little rock pool.
Maybe there's some crabs
in here.
At the moment, I don't have
any other responsibilities
in my life other than
to my partner,
my dog, and myself.
So I don't have
that fear of needing
to support something else.
So this is an opportunity for
me to completely start fresh.
And the $500,000 really
would help us
with the idea of buying a plot
of land, which we would like
to make our own homestead on.
Nothing.
I thought there was
something moving,
but that was just
my stomach again.
Easy, gut, easy.
you're not happy.
I don't know if these crabs
come up on land or not.
I'm assuming under
wet rocks and the such.
Is it something I ate?
Is it something
I haven't eaten?
Okay.
What the [bleep] is going on?
My gut's really hurting.
All right.
I need to clean up somehow.
Right.
So much for exploring
the coastline.
I don't know
if that's from the water
or from the prickly pear
or just from a few days
of not really eating.
Or maybe I've been eating
the wrong stuff,
drinking the wrong things.
I don't know if this is
just a one-off episode
or if this is gonna last
all night.
Got to get a fire going
before this gets too bad.
What I do know is that
quite often,
when things are quick onset,
you vomit first.
And then the diarrhea
comes later.
But this has gone
the other way around.
I just vomited up
whatever was in me.
So is this gonna be something
that lasts two or three days?
Oh, my belly hurts.
I don't have a way
of telling at the moment,
so I need to get through
tonight to reassess.
My head's cold again now.
My whole body aches.
And I don't want
to drink water,
but I should.
Just a sip.
Please stay down.
Ooh.
Okay.
Let's try and go back to sleep.
I could sit here and wait out
a couple more days.
Is it worth it?
Okay, okay, okay.
This is Jit.
I'm officially tapping out.
I wasn't scared
of being on my own,
but I'm scared of my health.
Here comes the boat.
Last night I ended up
soiling myself.
So I thought, okay,
let's just come back to base
and sort myself out.
And then, throughout the night,
was just the vomiting,
the stabbing pains.
It just doesn't feel
like a situation which
I can recover from myself.
There's a lot of people who
have supported me to get here.
Yeah, four days doesn't feel
like I've done them justice.
At the same time, my brother
said, trust your gut.
My gut is not being nice.
And my partner said,
come back in one piece.
So I'm trying to honor those.
I used to think that
my main values were honesty
and courage,
and now I'm definitely
seeing that health has crept
into one of my main values.
It's sad to leave
because there was still
so much I hadn't
explored, but I know
it was the right thing to do.
I think a lot of people
talk about strategies
and have in their mind these
romanticized ideas of what
it's like to be out here--
their ideal shelter
built in their head.
They're going to catch
this on day one.
They'll build that there.
And it's fantastic,
and you do need a plan,
but no plan survives.
Good morning, Africa.
All alone.
Not another human
to bear witness.
It's like
the Wild West out here.
They put me in
the middle of a [bleep] desert.
I'm really thirsty
right now, man.
It's super hot.
Everybody's got
to be dehydrated.
Big old scorpion.
Holy [bleep].
Rocks just came off that cliff.
Baboons are not happy with me.
All the animals can see
every move I make.
I don't think they
like the new intruders.
Something's moving around.
I can't tell what it is.
Oh, my God, it's a snake.
Wildabeest,
coming right to me.
Look at the size of that.
Yes.
All the planning,
the tips, and tactics,
and secrets, and stuff
you work out in your brain--
, none of that matters.
That's what
I'm talking about.
No!
Gotcha!
There is no right way.
There's no manual,
there's no book to go to.
Please, God, help me
catch something.
- Wow!
- Freaking giraffe.
There's a nice big storm
coming through.
It appears my tarp
is not very waterproof.
Holy hell, we have a river.
Oh, my goodness.
Yes.
This whole journey is an
emotional roller coaster.
Gonna puke.
It's wild.
Give me the
out of this place.
Oh, God.
I'm so exhausted,
I can't keep going.
.
Even the idea of
drinking makes me feel sick.
I feel like this
is the best site.
I feel like it's got
everything you need,
and I'm just not in a place
where I can make it happen.
Something in my body is
saying this isn't going well.
I just can't get myself
down to get water.
So if I can't recover from
it without putting myself
at a lot of risk,
then I don't think
there's a positive outcome.
How are you feeling?
Yeah, a bit rough.
It's one of those things that
could just be a 24-hour bug.
I vomited a few times
overnight, yeah--
- Yeah.
- and had diarrhea.
No, just lightheaded, man.
Lightheaded?
Yeah.
Body aches, as well.
All the joints are achy.
OK.
Start feeding
you some nutrients,
and take it from there, OK?
It's amazing how
much of an impact
this experience can have
in such a short time.
And it's helped
me question what
I thought were my core values.
And that's OK, because I think
it's important to reassess
your values every so often.
I can safely say that
I would bump courage
to the side for health.
And that's an amazing
reflection and something
I hope to carry on as I get
home, to find other ways
of prioritizing my health--
whether it be my
physical health
or, like I said, my mental
health, or finding ways
to slow down and take time
to enjoy the small things.
Not stoked.
Nausea settling a little bit?
Yeah.
Take a set of vitals
on you, and then just
go through a little bit
of an assessment here.
Make sure there's no flags.
Then the stabbing pains
in the lower right subsided?
- It has subsided, yeah.
- OK.
Did it feel like
it was coinciding
with gas movement or anything?
Not that you noticed?
There was no rhythm to
it that I could work out.
OK.
It just came.
Yeah.
Any difficulties
breathing, respirations?
If I take too
deep a breath, then--
- You just feel that same--
- Feel like my heart hurts.
Yeah.
- You feel that same pressure?
Yes.
OK.
If I take a deep inhale.
And then, as best as
you're aware, last night,
no signs of fever?
No shivering, trembling?
I mean,
it was a chilly night.
Yeah.
I-- I was sweating.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, I was
sweating last night.
Dehydration can
cause many issues.
Any pain?
No, none.
Any down here?
Nothing.
I think rest, relaxation,
pushing fluids is really
going to give you that reboot.
Let's get you taken care of.
Because it was
only four days,
I don't know if I
got that opportunity
to really challenge whether
or not I could do this.
And that might be
something that hangs
over my head for a while.
But at the same time,
by leaving now
I'm gaining health.
Although it was short, the
time out there, I'm really
happy that I got to do that.